a new form of exercise vibration
training might just hold some promise
for people of an advanced age the old
folks I say exercise because it's tough
to characterize it like that yet as
we'll see it might provide some similar
benefits an analysis of 34 randomized
control trials researchers looked into
this unconventional method for improving
muscle strength and they specifically
included studies in older individuals
because muscle strength becomes more and
more of a health concern as we get older
we'll go over the results some key
nuances and how to use the information
at home I suppose before we uh get into
the analysis itself we should get some
background on vibration training itself
vibration training is literally a whole
body vibration that emanates from a
platform that oscillates up and down or
side toide the platform looks like this
looks like something that you might find
in the I don't know the Jets and but
it's actually one used in the studies so
these are definitely commercially
available essentially the mechanical
vibrations engage stabilizing muscles
engage the nervous system to constantly
adjust for frequency and amplitude of
the vibrations there's different
versions standing sitting and so on and
although things like resistance training
is usually recommended for improving
strength it can be intimidating or
implausible for some so could this
provide a similar benefit for that we'll
turn to this analysis focused on people
who were 60 years and older and included
men and women they focused on lower body
muscle strength improvements because uh
this is an area that is of the greatest
concern it's the part of the body that's
most affected by Falls for example which
can be debilitating and even deadly so
let's focus on the knee extensors those
are the muscles at the front of your leg
like the quadricep muscles primarily
clearly an area of great importance when
catching ourselves from a front-facing
fall like tripping looking over the data
the different conditions of participants
included in the analysis are the
headings on the left side the top being
healthy yet elderly individuals then
sarcopenic individuals so people with
Beyond normal reduced muscle function
then two more groups related to Frailty
essentially people who are in such
compromised shape that they may be
institutional or under constant
supervision because their day-to-day
function is difficult to achieve now see
the zero line there that's the null
effect line so if the diamond moves to
the right it indicates there's a muscle
strengthening effect of the vibration
training so further evidence in
Portuguese at the bottom and since I am
fluent in Portuguese I will read it and
translate vibo vibo V
I'm not fluid in Portuguese not even a
little bit but it means vibration
looking that obviously sounded a lot
more Italian than anything looking all
these looking at all these different
subgroups over there is a positive
effect for older healthy individuals and
frail individuals but not for the
sarcopenic individuals nor for the low
functionality individuals the reason
being that the diamond is in contact
with the null line now there are a
variety of reasons for that but the
bottom line is that there aren't enough
studies to make a clear assessment
except in older healthy individuals yet
the next question that we have to ask
ourselves is how much of an effect the
data is presented in standard format
which means that the interpretation is a
bit more difficult skipping the
statistics lesson we're looking at a
moderate effect across the board so
likely noticeable and worthwhile now
another question that we should ask
ourselves is if the intensity of the
vibration makes a difference fortunately
the researchers looked into that too
before we get to that I pulled the
different protocols across uh the most
effective studies and put together a
simple protocol for anyone interested in
giving vibration training a shot it's
available for the physionic Insiders
along with all my other work the link is
in the description if you're interested
okay one of the most important variables
in ex exercise and also here is the
intensity of the training in this case
there are a number of parameters that
researchers can change but magnitude is
one of the most important so the
researchers split the studies According
to which studies use vibration training
at a low magnitude and those that
trained at a high magnitude the cut off
was
4.4g let's focus on the biggest data set
the knee extensors again here we're
looking at both magnitudes the left is
below 4.4g and the right is above 4.4g
and well although again limited studies
it doesn't seem to matter both work
again both are mostly driven by the
healthier older individuals although
individual studies indicate some
potential benefit in less healthy
situations too okay but as far as I know
there's no G meter on these devices so
we have to calculate it but you can
remain calm I won't make you do the math
I'll give you all the information as
needed by the way the G stands for
gravitational acceleration which is what
fighter pilots and astronauts have to
deal with well at least as far as I'm
aware look for an amendment to this
video if uh that was wrong I'm no
physicist obviously the context is
entirely different we're not trying to
flatten Grandpa under massive G forces
as he cork screws through the sky it's a
hilarious image though okay a few things
before we wrap this up one I know the
researchers included what did I say uh
30 something studies it seems like a lot
of studies but that's because the
studies look at different uh parts of
the leg it's a good amount of
consistency across muscle groups but
there's a lot more data that we need to
have on these subpopulations of people
like those with sarcopenia for example
second about 50% of the studies use
vibration training compared again
nothing so not exactly a shock that we
might see an effect the comparisons
against exercise are very weak so I'm
ignoring those the point being we don't
really know if this is better than
resistance training but we do know that
it's better than nothing and it's not
just a little bit better but noticeably
better I just want to make sure that
you're aware of those two important
points now how do we use this well G or
gravitational acceleration is based on a
formula and that formula is dependent on
two things frequency and Peak
displacement for a G of 4.4 like we
discussed earlier you would want to set
your vibration device to 2 mm
displacement at a 23 HZ frequency if you
increase either of those values you have
increased the G and if you reduce one or
both then you are reducing the G
but as we noted higher and lower seem to
be effective and as a final
consideration the lowest G used in the
studies was
0.1g which is very low but that was used
in the frail individuals which makes
sense since uh you have to be careful as
it can be pretty critical for healthy
older individuals as a reminder that's
defined as over 60 in this analysis the
G was 0 three at minimum and still
effective in that study or like I said
if you want it all conveniently laid out
for you I have a protocol laid out for
the physionic Insiders again Link in the
description so where does that leave us
what's the short version one vibration
training works for improving muscular
strength in people 60 and older with
noticeable effects two more data is
necessary but it seems effective for
everyone who is reasonably healthy and
there's some evidence that it may also
be helpful for people who are classified
as frail three evidence currently
suggests that any gravitational
acceleration so G is effective even very
low levels as we discussed earlier in
more detail but there are other ways of
regaining muscle function even at very
Advanced stages of life I cover them in
this next video thanks for tuning in